A Guide to the Edward L. Stone/Borderland Coal Company Papers
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
The Borderland Coal Company never fully recovered from the trouble that paralyzed its mines in 1920. The 1920's were a very depressed period for the mining industry in general and the depression of 1929 brought prices to an all time low. Coal production fell precipitously from 1927-1933 although there seemed to be a slight upturn that year. In 1927, L. E. Armentrout resigned from the company and a year later the Borderland Coal Sales Company was dissolved due to lack of business. The Norfolk and Chesapeake Coal Company became exclusive agents for the sale of Borderland coal. At a meeting of the Borderland Coal Company's board of directors in 1929, it was stated that since the market for coal was so poor, it hardly paid to keep the mines going. The Borderland Coal Company mines were only worked four days during the entire month of May 1932. In a letter from Edward L. Stone to a Borderland Coal Company creditor, Stone wrote that as the Borderland Coal Company did not have the money to pay its debts, all creditors would have to wait for their money, and that he hoped that he could avoid declaring the Borderland Coal Company bankrupt. In 1934 Stone received a letter from a stockholder consoling him for having to "lose Borderland Coal." Apparently the company was then out of business.
The demise of the Borderland Coal Company was the result of broad national trends; the product of their mines was of high quality, and in good supply. The problem of labor and unionization paralyzed the Borderland Coal Company. Lack of production in the mines meant that the Borderland Coal Company could not pay dividends which affected their stockholders. The bad mining conditions, a lack of demand for coal and low market prices made it impossible for the Borderland Coal Company to recover. The return of the coal-rich region of Alsace-Lorraine to France meant that our allies no longer needed American coal. Domestic demand increased, but it did not compensate for decreased industrial use. The switch to alternative forms of energy such as oil, also damaged the coal industry. Although prosperity returned to the rest of the country, the coal industry never totally recovered, and the Borderland Coal Company was one of the victims.
Officers of the Borderland Coal Company: Edward Lee Stone --President ca. 1907-1919, Chairman of the Board 1919-ca. 1934; James P. Woods (attorney at law --U. S. Representative, 6th Virginia District) --Vice President ca. 1905-1922, President 1922-1932; L. E. Armentrout --Manager ca. 1905-1915, Vice President and Manager ca. 1915-1927; Ernest B. Fishburn --Secretary-Treasurer ca. 1905-1930
Officers of the Borderland Coal Sales Company: L. E. Armentrout --President; Edward Lee Stone --Vice President; James P. Woods --second Vice President; R. N. Osborne, Jr.--Secretary (discharged in 1924); W. W. Austin--Secretary.
A History of the Stone Printing and Manufacturing Company
The Stone Printing and Manufacturing Company of Roanoke, Virginia, was established in 1883 as the Bell Printing and Manufacturing Company. John P. Bell of Lynchburg served as president, and Samuel J. Fields of Abington, Virginia, served as manager. Edward L. Stone, the eventual chairman of the board, was then employed as a journeyman printer and pressman. In 1885, Stone succeeded Fields as the company's manager, and his brother, Albert A. Stone, joined the business.
At this time the company occupied a small site on Commerce Street in Roanoke, an area about twenty by twenty-five feet. In 1889 the plant was seriously damaged by fire, and within a few months, the company moved to larger quarters on the second and third floors of the Gale Building on Jefferson Street. Shortly thereafter, the controlling interest was purchased by Edward L. Stone, with the remainder of the stock being purchased by J. B. Fishburn and Albert A. Stone.
In 1892, the name of the company was changed to the Stone Printing and Manufacturing Company, and the company occupied a new, three-story building at 116 North Jefferson Street. In 1896, a duplicate building was added on the north side; in a few years another addition was placed at the rear. The company built another addition in 1902 but five years later the old structure was torn down and a new two-stories building, 210 x 110 feet, was completed. The new structure gave the Stone Printing Company 50,000 square feet of space, which is about 100 times the floor space originally occupied on Commerce Street. The company today occupies the same site on Jefferson Street.
In 1883 the capital stock of the company was $5,000.00, and in 1900, it was increased to $50,000.00. In 1910 the capital stock had grown to $350,000.00. All of the stock increases were taken, with one exception, by the original stockholders. Sales grew from $84,371.00 in 1900 to $179,433.78 in 1905, and from $253,781.15 in 1909 to a high of $608,174.36 in 1920.
Stone had considered selling his printing company to a British syndicate in 1912. He felt, however, that business was good and getting better and eventually decided to retain control. By 1920 the Stone Printing Company had customers in half the states in the union and in some foreign countries. Between 1920 and 1929, however, sales showed a steady decline. In 1929 they fell to $399,701.43 and declined throughout the depression.
The Stone Printing Company's most important business came from railroads as the company printed tariff and rate schedules as well as tickets. Since the railroad rates changed rapidly during the early 1900's, railroad printing was very lucrative. The principal railroad customer and in fact, the largest customer, of the Stone Printing Company was the Norfolk and Western Railroad. In 1910 the Norfolk and Western Railroad accounted for $85,652.60 in sales. Combined with the sales to other railroads in 1910, the total of railroad sales was approximately $193,000.00 of a total of $339,678.92 --well over half of the total sales of the Stone Printing Company.
Commercial printing comprised the second largest source of the Stone Printing Company's business, accounting for $135,110.32 of a total $608,174.36 in 1920. The fourth largest amount of business, after the Norfolk and Western Railway, other railroads, and commercial printing, was school and college printing. The Stone Printing Company printed the yearbooks for the University of Virginia, the Georgia Institute of Technology, the University of Mississippi, Randolph-Macon College, Hollins College, Virginia Polytechnic Institute, and others.
The profit margin in printing often was small, and thus costs had to be carefully controlled. Edward L. Stone was a commissioner of the American Printers Cost Commission which kept a close watch on printing costs and tried to keep them down. Another serious problem that bothered Stone Printing Company was unionization. As most Roanoke printing shops, Stone Printing Company was an open shop where either union or non-union people could be employed. The company's officers did not penalize or prevent workers from joining the union. The International Typographical Union, however, put pressure on Edward Stone to turn his establishment into a closed shop, that is, a shop that would hire only union members, pay union wages, and abide by union rules. Paying union wages did not trouble Stone because he already paid more than the union scale in most cases. For example, in 1905 when the union scale was $13.50 per week, Stone pointed out that while two of his employees received less and one received the union wage, over forty workers received between $15.00 and $25.00 per week. Stone felt it folly to pay all workers the same because, he said, "some are so much better than others."
Edward Stone's paternalistic attitude toward his employees is reflected in a collection of letters exchanged with his workers. Forced to fire an employee who lied about being able to work on a printing press, Stone lent him the money to go to printing school, and re-hired him when he had learned the trade. Another worker left the company without notice, heading home to Lexington, Virginia. When the employee needed money to return to Roanoke, Stone lent it to him with the understanding that the employee would never again leave without asking Stone's permission. Another employee left Stone without notice to work for another printing firm, but when the employee wanted his old job back, Stone gave it to him. Stone frequently lent money to his employees, and did not press them for repayment.
Many of the union's rules, however bothered Stone. Among the ones he objected to were (1) in all cases when it became necessary to reduce the working force of an office, the last person hired should be the first dropped; (2) in machine composition, all work must be time work and no piece work should be allowed; (3) no member of the International Typographical Union should engage in a speed contest either by hand composition or on machines, and violation of this rule was to be punished by a fine of not less than $25.00, or by suspension; (4) an eight hour day (Stone Printing had a 9 to 9-1/2 hour day); and (5) no one holding active membership in a local union should sign any individual or private contract with any employer, agreeing to work for any stated time, length, or conditions as the union alone was to have the power to contract for conditions, wages, and hours. This fifth stipulation bothered Stone the most for he firmly believed that an employee should perform whatever duty Stone demanded of him.
On November 20, 1907, there was a union strike in Roanoke. The union men employed by the Stone Printing Company walked out, and the union formed a picket line in front of the Stone Printing Company. Stone wrote to Joel Cuthin, Mayor of Roanoke: "We have never been opposed to the union, but we have objected to having them run our business, unless they acquired it by ownership." The union put pressure on the Stone Printing Company. A memo to Edward Stone from Albert Stone dated 1915 told of some Stone Printing Company material being returned by certain Roanoke merchants because they did not bear the union label. The amount of material returned, however, was very small. The union pressure placed on Stone was generally peaceful and there was no violence or destruction. After the unsuccessful strike, Stone took back all of his union men.
After 1920 the company's sales and profits declined. In 1927, Albert Stone, who had assumed the presidency of the company, commissioned Ernst and Ernst, financial analysts, to examine the operation of Stone Printing and make recommendations for improving business. The analysts found Stone Printing to be an innovative company which sought and found new markets such as school and college printing and the printing of calendars, and which had sound leadership. Ernst and Ernst felt that it was a change in economic conditions, not the company itself, that caused the company's problems. Competition had changed and grown in intensity by 1920, making the ability to sell most important. The analysts recommended the creation of a sales department coupled with more aggressive selling techniques.
Later, Albert Stone, Jr., Edward Stone's nephew, claimed that it was the reluctance of the Stone Printing Company to cut prices during the depression of 1919-1922 that caused the company's problems. He claimed that by the time the company did cut its prices, Stone Printing had lost many of its most valued customers, and suggested a closer watch of costs coupled with an expansion of the calendar line. Although these suggestions were followed, business did not improve.
When the Great Depression hit in 1929, business worsened. Loyal customers and a solid financial base kept the Stone Printing Company from bankruptcy. Edward Stone's health was failing by 1929, and most of the company's affairs were passed on to his brother Albert. In a letter from Edward Stone to the board of directors in 1930, he wrote:
the years operations to date, with vastly improved selling efforts, has only brought us the same volume of business that we had last year but the increased organization expense, incident to this extra selling effort, and the extraordinary competition in the matter of price, has prevented us from obtaining prices that we should really obtain for our products.
Edward Stone recommended a reduction in salaries across the board from the president on down, and layoffs of certain personnel.
When Franklin D. Roosevelt first initiated his New Deal program in 1933, Edward Stone was apprehensive. In a letter dated July 26, 1933, he wrote:
We would like the best in the world to go along with the National Industrial Recovery Act, and be able to wire President Roosevelt an affirmative reply in connection with the agreement addressed "To Every Employer."
But to do so, with my modest knowledge of economics, would mean arbitrary action on our part, with a "blind faith" that we do not possess.
If we still further reduce the working hours to 35 per week (as the New Deal suggested) the increased cost of production reaches the geometric progression stage, with the result that our losses on current contracts, which we see no way of passing along to our customers until we would actually see no way of meeting our payroll or meeting our bills, would mean disaster.
Listening in over the radio last night I understand that 5,000 or more telegrams had been received by the President indicating unconditional acceptance of the Agreement. It is quite possible that we should do likewise, regardless, just as we offered ourselves, body and resources, in wartime.
I am giving expression to these thoughts even though I feel the "patriotic" thing for us to do may be to go ahead, "blindly," and in spite of our objections or reasons for not doing so, and sign the agreement.
Very Sincerely,
Edward L. Stone
Chairman of the Board
Clearly, Stone expected no miracles, but he went along with the N.I.R.A. and generally supported Roosevelt. There are references to increasing business by 1937. Correspondence ends the following year with Edward Stone's death. The Stone Printing Company, however, is in business to this very day.
Scope and Content Information
These papers fill 455 special four-inch Hollinger storage boxes (ca. 150 linear feet) and span the years 1895-1937. There are three major series: Edward L. Stone's papers re his personal life and diversified business, professional, and civic concerns; papers concerned with his principal business, the Stone Printing and Manufacturing Company of Roanoke, Virginia; and those papers concerned with the Borderland Coal Company of West Virginia and Kentucky of which Stone was the principal officer for many years. Because these series basically are composed of Stone's personal papers, and because there are interrelationships between material in one series and that in another, the series have been maintained in the boxes in the order in which they were found.
The papers are rich in material for many types of studies. Because Stone's major concern was his printing business, there is a great amount of material about that business, its labor problems, economic problems, its professional associations, relationships with its customers --especially the railroads --and so on. Because Mr. Stone collected medieval manuscripts and examples of fine printing that formed a great private library, there is, in his personal papers, a good deal of correspondence and material about this special interest. His personal papers also contain considerable material about his diversified business and civic interests. And the records of the Borderland Coal Company--which Mr. Stone operated either as president or as chairman of the board for twenty-seven years--are rich in information concerning this vital industry, its periods of economic success and decline, its relationships with the railroads that moved its products, and its labor problems.
Organization
After arrival at the University, the collection was placed in the stack areas of the then division of Rare Books and Manuscripts of the Library, and was shelved in close proximity to another large collection received only a year before, that of the Low Moor Iron Company. The two comprised the largest group of material in the division at the time, a group that, unfortunately, was rarely used by researchers as there were no finding aids to the mass, and interested researchers were intimidated by the problems of research in the papers.
The collections remained in the stacks until 1958 when expansion space in the division's storage area was reduced to a minimum by the successful collecting program of the intervening years. A review of the collections and their use showed that the Stone collection and the Low Moor Iron Company papers were rarely consulted, and it was decided to move them out of the division's quarters to provide storage space for collections that were being used by researchers.
Space was located in the attic of a student dormitory, and the division prepared the papers for long-term storage by removing them from the old letter boxes in which they had arrived. Each bundle of papers was placed between sheets of gray, newspaper-storage cardboard sheets; the spine titles of the old letter boxes were copied onto the cardboard sheets, and the bundle was wrapped in brown paper, tied up with string, and numbered in a coded sequence.
The collections remained in the attic of Lefevre House until the fall of 1976 when, after the receipt of a grant from the National Endowment for the Humanities for the processing of the two collections, they were transported to the Alderman Library building once more In the Library's receiving room, the bundles were cleaned in the dust hood, untied and unwrapped, and the contents transferred into gray, Hollinger storage boxes before transfer into the storage areas of the Manuscripts Department for processing. The coded numbers on the bundles were recorded but proved to be of no use in restoring order to the papers, badly out of sequence from their many moves over the years. Nor did the spine titles and dates from the original letters boxes prove to be of any particular use in organizing the collection.
Once processing work was completed at the end of the summer of 1978, the Stone Papers were transferred back to the dormitory attic as space in the Alderman Library building remained short, and it was felt that adequate service on the Stone Papers could be maintained from the attic now that a guide to the papers had been prepared. (N.B. The Stone papers were removed from the dormitory attic and transferred to the University Library's high-density remote storage facility following its opening in the mid-1990s.)
The word "organization" is used here with considerable diffidence, for any researcher studying the lists of box contents that follow will realize quickly that there is no organization in the usual sense of the word.
As previously noted, the Stone papers were subjected to a number of moves before processing began, and, unfortunately, there seems to have been little organization of the papers in Mr. Stone's files in his Roanoke office. Presumably, he and his staff could locate material that was needed from the files, but at the time that processing began in the fall of 1976, no discernible scheme of organization could be determined.
The first step was to review the series of coded numbers placed on the bundles of papers before they were moved to the dormitory attic, but these did not provide any sort of useful organization. Next, the spine titles of the original letter boxes were reviewed (they had been copied onto the gray cardboard sheets before the move to the dormitory attic), but they, too, proved useless.
These steps having provided no scheme, and after a considerable hiatus due to a turnover in student processors on the collection, the new student processors were instructed to begin a box-by-box inventory of the contents of the collection. During this inventory, old folders were replaced with acid-free ones, and the original folder headings were copied onto the new ones. Some removal of papers clips was accomplished, and the materials were reviewed and notes were taken for the guide.
The processors found that Mr. Stone's papers were comprised of three series. One was devoted to his personal affairs, and contained material about his diverse business interests outside his two major ones, and about his civic and professional interests, as well as papers from his private life. The second series contained the papers from his major business and "first love" the Stone Printing and Manufacturing Company of Roanoke; and the third series included a wealth of material about the Borderland Coal Company, an enterprise that Mr. Stone served for twenty-seven years, first as president and later, as chairman of the board.
For a long time, we considered separating the three series of papers, and the processors evolved a good system of colored slips clipped to the boxes to identify material from each series contained in a box. However, as they neared the end of their inventory, the processors became convinced, and argued successfully that the series should not be separated. Basically, all these papers are Mr. Stone's private papers as he was the major stockholder in the Stone Printing Company and it was very much a personal operation. There are interrelationships between material that was found standing in different folders in the same box, and the processors correctly feared that drastic reorganization would destroy those relationships. Thus, we decided to accept their argument, and the box contents were allowed to remain as we found them.
A certain amount of movement of boxes within the collection probably would ease use of it. But what processing was accomplished on this project took far longer than had been anticipated, and there was no time in the late spring of 1978, when the processors had to complete their work with the project, to undertake a mass movement of material. Thus, they stand in the order in which we found them at the beginning of the project.
As has been stated above, the three series of papers in this collection (Stone Personal; Borderland Coal Co.; and Stone Printing and Mfg. Co.) have not been physically separated and are scattered throughout the collection. However, in the container listing which follows the three series have been separated. Therefore, the listing for the Edward L. Stone Personal Papers series begins with Box 11 of the collection because that is the first box in which Stone's personal papers can be found. (Boxes 1-10 appear in the listing for the Borderland Coal Co. series.) This also means that if a box contains material from more than one series it will have more than one entry in the listing, so that to find a complete listing of a particular box a researcher might need to look at the listing for each of the three series. In addition, some of the box entries in the listing are slightly out of order, so that if a box appears to have no entry or only a partial entry, in a particular series the entry is sometimes picked up on the next page of the listing.
Listings of oversize material are located at the end of the listing for each series.
Container List
- Edward L. Stone Personal Papers
  - Stone Personal: rare books correspondence, 1931 June -1936 Aug (Box Box 11)
  - Charity, 1936 Oct -Nov (Box Box 11)
  - Correspondence, 1931 Oct -1938 April (Box Box 11)
  - Insurance, 1920 June -1934 Jan (Box Box 13)
  - Correspondence with John C. Hill of Typothetae of Baltimore, 1920 March -1935 Jan (Box Box 13)
  - Correspondence with Claude V. Hines, 1921 Jan -1933 Jan (Box Box 13)
  - Correspondence with Hollbrook Jackson, 1931 June -1935 Aug (Box Box 13)